{
  "reference_number": "149",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "Make it possible to revise year-on-year, eg: if uptake of EV’s exceeds expectations, target can be adjusted accordingly. Don’t want\n people to think they can just have a year off for other people’s good behaviour ;-)"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "Focussing on CO2 ignores the ‘bump’ that CH3 gives to atmospheric carbon"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "Carbon trading is already being relied on by many significant emitters. Yes, plant as many trees as you can, including native flora in\n appropriate places, but we’ll still need to buy offsets imho. Especially if storm damage is to be taken into account."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Would love to see us hit the target earlier. Modulo Trump doesn’t set off WW3 & create Nuclear winter. All bets are off in that scenario."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Specific, achievable & measurable goals always win over handwave aspirations. Make sure that measurement of effects of goals is\n built in from the start!"
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "Needs to have some clarity around the global commitment that NZ is signed up to, & some structure & rigour to prevent frivolous\n\n changes or suspension of targets. Don’t let another John Key do to this, what he did to the Cullen Fund - our Superannuation is\n flawed now from 9 years of deferred contributions from Gov’t."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "No forecasting tool ever can be 100% accurate. Unexpected events occur, both in the environment and in the economy. It would be\nhugely unrealistic for there to be no capacity for adjustments to be made, to conform to irl circumstances on the planet.... ;-/"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "MY hardline position would be to ban all oil industry representatives from any position within the Commission. I realise this is an outlier\nposition to hold. I consider it valid, when the history of oil industry interference with uptake of science around climate change is taken\n\ninto account. They will fight their way into the sunset. We don’t have to consider their profit losses - they had no consideration for the\nlives of millions of people who will be displaced by sea level rise, or storm damage."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Transparency and accountability to citizens is very important. ‘Commercial sensitivities’ have been used to stifle citizen dissent for too\nlong. A broader understanding of what can be done for a just transition is necessary to allay fears that have been promulgated by\n\nthose with vested interests in the status quo."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "*Sunset industries - need to have re-training/ redeployment options up front with the reduction budgeting. *New tech - need to\nensure training of people who will work in these areas is prioritised - whether that be subsidies for (re-)training or scholarships in\n\nparticular areas of engineering/tech. *Need good PR for non-technical citizens so that they can be adequately informed about\noptions during transition period. *Need supports for low-income households as transition to low carbon lifestyle continues - maybe\n\nwith some ‘stick’ for landlords, etc, to get them moving on insulation, energy-efficient heating, solar panels, etc. Germany as an\nexemplar for solar panels on every roof. As transport fuels rise in cost, assistance to transition to EV’s might become a thing. *Local\ngovt buy-in on regional scale public transport upgrades, focus on getting people into mass transit & out of single occupant vehicles.\n\n*Framing inner-city intensification along energy-efficiency lines. Combine high density housing with access to community gardens for\nsustainable living solutions. This is frequently not considered in our provincial cities, who perceive themselves as having small\n\nfootprints & in no need of inner city intensification for housing, PT functions. *Industries & businesses may need assistance to see\nhow they can reduce waste, reduce carbon footprint, thus improving their own triple bottom lines. Perhaps a greater role for\n\nSustainable Business Network as leaders in transition to future sustainability. *Ag sector needs to be brought into the transition\ncarefully. One trip to Fieldays is enough to make a city person realise that farm equipment investment is a major in modern Ag - an EV\nfor the family is not the big concern, when you owe half the cost of an IH farm machine. Mechanisation & automation on farms has\n\nbeen about reducing staffing costs over the past generation - efficiencies of scale have been created, by using fossil fuels to replace\nhorses & humans. They’re not going to flip back to the 1930’s style of labour intensive farming without a fight, nor is there enough\n\ninvestment in producing machinery that doesn’t run on fossil fuels. The ‘burping cattle’ are just a minor nuisance inside the bigger\npicture of reliance on machinery to get the job done."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Using overseas examples as templates is a no brainer. EU & UK have been on this problem for decades, why reinvent the wheel?"
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Our mix of expertise needs to be broader than UK, due to Te Tiriti considerations. We have historically traded with a multitude of other\ncountries; this gives us strength in negotiation skills that the UK has lacked recently due to it’s reliance on EU-wide trade deals. Our\nCommission should be given tasking that draws on our already extensive skill base for international negotiation, so that our\n\nrelationships with other countries are fostered by our climate change decisions, not ruptured."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Impacts of climate disasters are already hitting local government budgeting. Making local adaptations (like moving roads or bridges)\n\nto give resilience to communities at risk, should not be hamstrung by inflexibility in carbon budgeting or legislation."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "As soon as possible, please. Communities like Edgecumbe & South Dunedin needed this five years ago. The presence of climate\nchange denying Mayor & some City Councillors in Hamilton is hampering attempts to plan for mitigation, adaptation & local changes\n\nto respond to climate change. Submissions from the public are set aside, poor decisions are being rushed through by those with\nvested interests and no science literacy. For the sake of the wider Waikato context, there needs to be legislation to guide local\ngovernment, to prevent perverse outcomes generated by self- interested individuals."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Insurance companies are already adjusting their risk tables. Businesses & organisations who fail to plan for adaptation risk having it\n\nthrust upon them by denial of insurance cover."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "Thanks to MfE & Minister for offering wide consultation with the public at large. Been gagged for nine long years! Nice to have a voice\n\nagain. I consent to the publication of my name with this submission. I do not wish my residential address to be published; my\nelectronic address is fine."
    }
  ]
}
